<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Michael Herold]]></title>
  <link href="http://michaelherold.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://michaelherold.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-04T16:46:28-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://michaelherold.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Michael Herold]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[michael@mherold.org]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome to my new blog!]]></title>
    <link href="http://michaelherold.github.io/blog/2013/11/04/welcome-to-my-new-blog/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-04T16:02:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://michaelherold.github.io/blog/2013/11/04/welcome-to-my-new-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Blogging has been something of a neglected hobby of mine for many years.
I have started several blogs that never progressed past a few posts.
Eventually, I scuttled each one, vowing to relaunch with a passion. This
is my latest attempt at a blog, without including any of my earlier
writings.</p>

<p>I struggled with the topic of this blog, as I have many interests that do
not have overlapping audiences. Because my life primarily revolves around
my work at the moment, I have decided to write about <strong>software
craftsmanship</strong>, with posts broken into a few separate categories:</p>

<ol>
<li><strong>Tutorials and informational posts.</strong> I have learned a lot about the
systems that I use every day by reading tutorials written on blogs. I
want to give back to that community by writing similar articles. I am
working mostly with Ruby (and Rails), so gems that I find useful will
be the initial focus of this category.</li>
<li><strong>Professional development.</strong> I am someone who really enjoys learning
different things that help me to better myself. Through the lens of
software craftsmanship, I will write posts about continuous education,
team dynamics, leadership, and productivity, and how you can improve
your skills and be the best software craftsman you can.</li>
<li><strong>Philosophy.</strong> I find that software craftsmanship has a lot of
inherent philosophy; whether it&rsquo;s the intricacies of open sourcing
your code, different software methodologies, or the ethics of writing
software, software craftsmen need to be aware of the ramifications of
their work and how the world views it.</li>
</ol>


<p>I plan to write periodically, though I haven&rsquo;t yet decided on an update
interval. Ideally, it will be three times per week, but as my time shifts
this will likely waver, as it is not my primary project. I will work on
the format for the blog as well, perhaps open sourcing the code behind it
at some point with information on how to use it for your own platform.</p>

<p>Please offer me feedback by commenting on the posts. I want to hear
your thoughts on my writing, what you find useful, what isn&rsquo;t useful, and
where I go astray. I&rsquo;m looking forward to hearing your opinions, whether
they align with my own or differ significantly.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
